James Sheldon

2342 W Bloomingdale Ave #205, Chicago IL 60647

Tel: 612.812.7356 jimsheldon@icloud.com http://jasheldo.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

Collaborative leader in data analytics in streamlining and improving processes through task automation in Python. Team player in partnering in finding the hidden meaning though data science best practices. Analytical researcher and academic instructor who creates and implements mathematical and conceptual ideas to better strategic outcomes.

EXPERIENCE

Business Info Developer Consultant Sr, Elevance Health, Chicago, IL

2021- present

Viewed as an expert in the development and execution of data mining analyses. Accomplishments include:

- Upskilling over one hundred Elevance Health employees in best practices and applications of Python
- Helped to create data pipeline to ingest and make useable the Payer Machine Readable Files from all payers
- Developed web scraping capabilities to effectively and efficiently retrieve hospital price transparency data
- Helped to identify the ability to map Anthem medical products to their respective networks
- Automated Cotiviti PDF invoice reconciliation
- Used additional web scraping capabilities to retrieve Medicaid state fee schedules

Senior Business Info Consultant, Anthem, Chicago, IL

2019-2021

Provide analytical support to the Cost of Care and/or Provider Contracting organizations. Focuses efforts on lowering claims costs, improving the quality of care, and increasing member and provider network satisfaction. Typically works with one provider type, e.g. physician, ancillary, or medical group. Provides advice and analytic support to Medical Directors, contract negotiators and management on cost of care issues to help reduce costs without compromising quality of care. Accomplishments include:

- Automated a business deliverable from a 3-5 business day turn around
- Developed and validated previously inaccessible network metrics for reporting enterprise-wide.
- Scripted numerous tasks that were previously unworkable in the organization.
- Collaborated with Data Science on big data fabric and deep learning projects.
- Construct and maintain the Network Dashboard in both Excel and Plotly Dash (Python package)

Senior Analyst, Revenue Modeling & Decision Support, Presence Health, Chicago, IL

2014-2019

Support and validate the Managed Care Network contracting activities through financial modeling and analysis and research financial impacts of alternative payment methods due to the Affordable Care Act (ACA). Accomplishments include:

- Contract modeling the positioned the organization to earn \$6 million in additional revenue
- Used Bundled Payment for Care Improvement (BPCI) program data to identify top underperforming physicians as well as sources of network leakage
- Build and maintain Python and SQL applications to warehouse and analyze Blue Cross & Blue Shield of Illinois experience reports, resulting in recovering \$2 million in underpayments.
- Provide detailed analytics, projections and forecasts for the entire C-Suite on multi-million dollar projects.

James Sheldon

2342 W Bloomingdale Ave #205, Chicago IL 60647

Tel: 612.812.7356 jimsheldon@icloud.com http://jasheldo.github.io

EDUCATION

Michigan Technological University, Houghton, MI

Master of Science, Mathematical Sciences, Earned August 2003

GPA - 3.50

Concentration: Applied Mathematics

Thesis: "Orientation Determination from Optical Scattering Patterns Generated by Ellipsoids of Revolution"

Awards: "Graduate Student Outstanding Teaching Award," 2003;

"Graduate Student Outstanding Service Award," 2002.

Michigan Technological University, Houghton, MI

Bachelor of Science, Mathematical Sciences, Earned December 2000

GPA: 3.00

Concentration: Applied Mathematics

Awards: "Outstanding Performance Award in Numerical Explorations in the Mathematical Sciences," 2000.

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

- Presenter, "What Colleges Can Offer New Faculty Members", American Mathematical Association of Two-Year Colleges (AMATYC) 2005 national conference, San Diego, CA
- J. Sheldon, "AMATYC 2004 National Conference: A New Member's Experience," MinnMATYC Newsletter, Fall 2004, vol. 2, p. 6-8
- Co-presenter, "Using Geometry Sketch Software", National Council of Teachers of Mathematics (NCTM)
 2002 national conference, Las Vegas, NV

GRANTS RECEIVED

- National Science Foundation CSEMS grant: "Advancing Careers in Computer Science, Engineering, and Mathematics", Co-Principal Investigator (Principal Investigator: Tim Wrenn), 9/2004-9/2008, \$385,000, Grant Number DUE-0422385.
- Exxon Mobil and Mathematical Association of America grant: Project ACCCESS: "Advancing Community College Careers: Education, Scholarship, and Service", Fellow, 1 of 26 selected nationwide. 9/2004-9/2005.
- National Science Foundation GK-12 Teaching Fellowship: "Graduate Teaching Fellows in K-12 Education",
- Mentee (Mentor: Dr. Beverly Baartmans), 9/2000-9/2002, \$1.5 million, Grant Number DUE-9979572.

CONTINUING EDUCATION

Data Science Specialization, Johns Hopkins University, 2016 (K7TXBPVB42Z7)
Data Scientist with R Specialization (23 courses) (DataCamp Cert # 7120)
Data Scientist with Python Specialization (22 courses) (DataCamp Cert # 24949)

CERTIFICATIONS

Snowflake SnowPro Core, 2023